AR-15 Gas System
As the expanding gases propel the
bullet down the barrel,
a portion escapes through the gas port.
This high pressure gas quickly
travels through the gas tube,
leading to a chamber between the bolt and the carrier.
The dwelltime is the time the bullet spends
between the gasport and the muzzle.
The pressure from the gastrapped behind the bullet
is necessary to cyclethe rifle.
The chamber between the bolt and carrier
acts as a pneumatic cylinder.
Since the bolt cannotmove forward,
the pressure forces the carrierto the rear.
As the bullet clears the muzzle, thepressure drops
and at this point the carrier has
picked up enough inertia to retract the bolt.
The two vents on the carrier
pass over the gas ringson the bolt
releasing the gases from the chamber.
The bolt carrier continues to the rear
as it extracts the empty shell case.